Hey, don't you think the most important thing to cooperate with AI is to make the order clear?
嘿，你不認為與 AI 合作最重要的是把要求講清楚嗎？
But to be honest, this is actually only half right.
但說實話，這其實只說對了一半。
The real challenge or the real headache is
真正的挑戰或真正的頭痛問題是
when AI responds to you, how do you know
當 AI 回應你時，你怎麼知道
whether the answer it gives you is a divine assist or a super big trouble?
它給你的答案是神助攻還是超大麻煩？
That's right, this is what we're going to talk about today.
沒錯，這就是我們今天要談的。
You know, AI is really strong, there's nothing to say about this.
你知道，AI 真的很強，這點沒什麼好說的。
But it has a wonderful feature.
但它有一個妙不可言的特點。
When it makes a mistake, it's so confident that it's even more secure than you and me.
當它犯錯時，它自信滿滿，甚至比你我還要保險。
So here's the question.
所以問題來了。
How are we going to tell if AI is really right?
我們怎麼判斷 AI 是否真的正確？
Or is it just a serious mess?
或者它只是一場天大的混亂？
Okay, so how do we solve this trust problem?
好的，那我們怎樣解決這個信任問題呢？
In fact, the key is to train a super important core skill.
實際上，關鍵是要訓練一項超級重要的核心技能。
You can imagine it as a safety net.
你可以把它想象成一個安全網。
With it, we can really exert the power of AI,
有了它，我們才能真正發揮 AI 的力量，
instead of being led by it.
而不是被它牽著鼻子走。
So you see, the key point is out.
所以你看，關鍵點就出來了。
The point is not just that you will give orders.
重點不只是你會下命令。
More importantly, it's actually how we judge what AI gives us.
更重要的是，我們其實是如何判斷 AI 給我們的東西。
This judgment is the core that really decides whether we cooperate or not.
這種判斷是真正決定我們是否合作的核心。
Okay, so the so-called judgment,
好的，所以所謂的判斷，
we give it a special noun called AI思辨能力.
我們給它一個特殊的名詞叫 AI 思辨能力。
What the hell is this?
這到底是什麼？
Let's talk about it.
讓我們來談談。
The so-called思辨能力, to be honest, is a kind of assessment ability.
所謂的思辨能力，說實話，是一種評估能力。
What is it?
它是什麼？
It's the process that AI produces for you.
它是 AI 為你生成的過程。
It's even the behavior of interacting with you.
甚至是它與你互動的行為。
I think there's a metaphor that's super close.
我認為有一個比喻超級恰當。
Just imagine it as your own AI control system.
就把它想象成你自己的 AI 控制系統。
Yes, it's a control system.
沒錯，它是一個控制系統。
It's used to ensure that every step AI takes is on the right track.
它用來確保 AI 採取的每一步都在正軌上。
Okay, we can think of it like this.
好的，我們可以這樣想。
Interacting with AI is basically two things.
與 AI 互動基本上是兩件事。
The first one is called the description ability.
第一個叫做表述能力。
This is to make a request.
這就是提出請求。
It's very intuitive to tell AI what you want.
很直觀地告訴 AI 你想要什麼。
But that's not enough.
但這還不夠。
The second one is what we've been talking about, the思辨能力,
第二個就是我們一直在談的，思辨能力，
which is to make a judgment.
即做出判斷。
Judgment what?
判斷什麼？
Judgment what AI gives you.
判斷 AI 給你的結果。
Is it what you want?
這是否是你想要的？
These two abilities can be said to complement each other.
這兩種能力可以說是相輔相成的。
One can't be less.
缺一不可。
Okay, next, in order to make it easier for everyone to get started,
好的，接下來，為了讓大家更容易上手，
we have three specific types of思辨能力.
我們有三種具體的思辨能力。
Once you understand these three types,
一旦你理解了這三種，
you can immediately use them in your work.
你就能立即在工作中運用它們。
It's really super practical.
真的非常實用。
The first one is also the most intuitive and easy to understand.
第一種也是最直觀、最容易理解的。
We call it the result of思辨.
我們稱之為結果思辨。
In other words, it's to judge whether the product that AI finally gives out is good or not.
換句話說，就是判斷 AI 最終給出的產物是否好。
Its accuracy and value are all counted.
它的準確性和價值都要算。
Simply put, it's to directly look at the results and evaluate the product.
簡單來說，就是直接看結果並評估產物。
How do you evaluate the product?
你如何評估這個產物？
You can ask yourself a few questions as a check list.
你可以問自己幾個問題作為檢查清單。
Is this product actually right?
這個產物真的是對的嗎？
Is its structure and logic consistent?
它的結構和邏輯是否前後一致？
Does it meet my initial requirements?
它是否符合我最初的需求？
These are all very important.
這些都非常重要。
But I think the most important question is,
但我認為最重要的問題是，
did it really solve my problem?
它真的解決了我的問題嗎？
Did it really tie me in?
它真的幫到我了嗎？
Okay, the second type of思辨能力 is called process思辨.
好的，第二種思辨能力叫做過程思辨。
This is more advanced.
這是更高級的。
It not only looks at the results,
它不僅看結果，
but also the process and method for AI to get this result.
還要看 AI 得出這個結果的過程和方法。
Why is this important?
為什麼這很重要？
Because if the task is very complicated,
因為如果任務很複雜，
you only look at the final answer.
你只看最終答案。
In fact, you will be confused, right?
實際上你會很困惑，對吧？
So we have to check whether the AI thinking process is reliable or not.
所以我們必須檢查 AI 的思考過程是否可靠。
So in the process of cooperation,
所以在合作的過程中，
we have to open our eyes and pay attention to some red light information.
我們必須睜大眼睛，注意一些紅燈信息。
For example, is the logic of AI strange?
例如，AI 的邏輯是否很奇怪？
Or is it always stuck in a small detail and can't turn over?
或者它總是卡在某個小細節上無法轉身？
What's worse is that sometimes it will also beat the wall and repeat the same argument.
更糟的是，有時它還會原地踏步，重複同樣的論點。
These problems are to be caught by process思辨.
這些問題需要通過過程思辨來發現。
Okay, the third type is more detailed.
好的，第三種方式更詳細。
It's called performance思辨.
它叫作績效思辨。
It's not about the production,
它不是關於成果，
it's not about the process,
也不是關於過程，
but the quality of your interaction with AI itself.
而是關於你與 AI 本身互動的品質。
To be honest,
說實話，
how does it feel when you two work together?
你們倆一起工作時感覺如何？
Is it smooth?
流暢嗎？
So what we want to evaluate is the overall feeling of interaction.
所以我們想評估的是互動的整體感受。
Do you think this cooperation is smooth and efficient?
你認為這個合作流暢且高效嗎？
Or do you think it's stuck and nagging?
還是你覺得卡頓又囉嗦？
Is the way AI communicates with you helpful?
AI 與你溝通的方式有幫助嗎？
Do you understand it?
你理解它嗎？
Is it right to change it?
改變它是正確的嗎？
If you make this interaction link smooth,
如果你讓這個互動環節順暢，
your cooperation relationship will get better and better.
你們的合作關係會越來越好。
Okay, so we've finished evaluating,
好的，所以我們完成了評估，
and then the most valuable part of the思辨能力 is here.
那麼思辨能力最有價值的部分就在這裡。
It's not over after evaluation,
評估後並不是結束，
but it's going to drive our next step.
而是要驅動我們的下一步。
In other words,
換句話說，
it's going to turn our judgment into a specific feedback
它要把我們的判斷轉化為具體的反饋
and form an ongoing cycle of progress.
並形成持續進步的循環。
Look, this is a complete co-operation cycle.
看，這是一個完整的合作循環。
It's simple.
很簡單。
First, you use description to give instructions.
首先，你用描述來下達指令。
Second, AI produces the result for you.
其次，AI 為你產生結果。
Third, you use思辨 to evaluate the result.
第三，你用思辨來評估結果。
Finally, fourth,
最後，第四，
you give feedback according to your assessment
你根據你的評估給出反饋
to adjust and optimize your next command.
來調整和優化你的下一個命令。
This circle keeps turning and turning.
這個循環不斷轉動。
The quality of your cooperation will get better and better
你們合作的品質會越來越好
like climbing stairs.
就像爬樓梯一樣。
Okay, we've talked so much.
好的，我們已經談了這麼多。
In fact, everything is back to the most important point.
實際上，一切都回到了最重要的一點。
That is,
那就是，
no matter how strong and powerful AI will become in the future,
無論 AI 未來會變得多麼強大和強力，
our human roles will always be indispensable.
我們人類的角色將永遠不可或缺。
There is a sentence here
這裡有一句話
that I think is really good.
我認為這真的很好。
It says,
它說，
through the cultivation of your思辨能力,
通過培養你的批判性思維能力，
you can ensure that your cooperation with AI
你可以確保你與 AI 的合作
is always led by human judgment.
始終由人類判斷主導。
That's right.
沒錯。
This is what we want.
這正是我們想要的。
This is the real effective way to use AI.
這是使用 AI 的真正有效方式。
So, in the end,
所以，最後，
the purpose of our efficient use of AI
我們有效使用 AI 的目的
is never to replace human thinking.
絕不是要取代人類的思考。
Absolutely not.
絕對不是。
It's to enhance our thinking.
而是增強我們的思考。
And this思辨能力
而這種批判性思維能力
is the key skill
是關鍵技能
that allows us to sit firmly on the driver's seat
讓我們能夠牢牢坐在駕駛座上
in this human-machine cooperation relationship.
在這種人機合作的關係中。
Finally,
最後，
I also want to leave a question for you.
我也想給你留下一個問題。
You can think about it.
你可以思考一下。
When you work with AI,
當你與 AI 合作時，
you are the only one
只有你
who can make that unique judgment.
能做出那個獨特的判斷。
What is it?
它是什麼？
I think the answer to this question
我認為這個問題的答案
may be the most important value
可能是最重要的價值
you have in this age of AI.
你在這個 AI 時代所擁有的。